# Jeff Barnes

# Software Engineer

#### Personal

#### Address

511 E 46th PI, Anchorage, AK 99503

#### Phone

+1-907-903-4082

#### E-mail

jeff.barnes@gmail.com

#### Linked-In

www.linkedin.com/in/jefferymbarnes

#### Skills

## Programming Languages

TypeScript, JavaScript, C, C++, Java, HTML, CSS, Python, Perl, Swift, Ruby, Assembly, SQL, Rust

## Platforms

Docker, Linux, Windows, VmWare, Mac OS X, AIX, Solaris, HP-UX, UNIX

## Networking

Distributed Systems, TCP/IP, SAN, Fibre Channel, SCSI

#### **Databases**

MongoDb, CouchDb, SQL Server, MySQL, PostgreSQL, IndexedDb

#### Misc

Git, SVN, PowerPC, Multithreading, Parallel Computing, Database Design, High Availability Software engineer with 20+ years professional software development experience. Lifelong passion for learning new technologies with experience in a breadth of software languages and frameworks. Demonstrated ability to work in large teams and individually.

## **Experience**

## Software Engineer, GCI

Engineering & Architecture, Automation & Optimization Anchorage, AK — 2019 - Present

- Maintain internally developed full-stack application for Site Management, Project
  Management, and Site Maintenance activities. Responsible for front-end Angular web app,
  back end Node.js code, configuration of VMs for deployment and writing and maintaining
  end-to-end test suite.
- Developed software and architecture to capture and process cellular performance metrics and enable performance monitoring of a multi-vendor cellular network. (Rust, SQL)
- Enabled integration between fault monitoring and ticketing platforms. (Perl)
- Provided real-time data feed from asset management database to ticketing platform.
   (Typescript, SQL)
- · Mentor junior developers.

## Software Engineer, GCI (Elwood Staffing, Opti Staffing)

Anchorage, AK - 2015 - 2019

- Developed a business critical application for viewing networking information, managing network changes, and tracking project status.
- Using leading edge open source technologies such as Angular, MongoDB, CouchDB and Node.js to enable a responsive mobile friendly experience.
- Designed application architecture and middleware necessary to interface with legacy business products.
- Managed full application development life cycle, including development, testing, integration and deployment using modern DevOps software techniques.
- · Mentor junior developers to build a functional cross-disciplinary team.

## Advisory Software Engineer, IBM

Tucson, AZ / Anchorage, AK - 2007 - 2012

- Led team of 4-5 developers supporting IBM DS8000 Storage System SCSI and Fibre channel protocols.
- Developed error recovery and availability firmware for IBM XIV Storage System.
- Helped develop routines for storing compressed and encrypted data.
- Designed interoperability features for IBM DS8000 Storage System and AIX UNIX to support disaster recovery scenarios.
- · Mentored and trained new team members.
- Provided project time estimates managed resource allocation.
- Traveled abroad to perform problem analysis on site at customer facilities.

## Staff Software Engineer, IBM

Tucson, AZ - 2002 - 2007

- Development and release of the IBM DS8000 Storage System, focus on SCSI and Fibre Channel protocols.
- Enabled industry leading SAN environments by designing and implementing advanced metadata management algorithms.
- Designed Java based GUI client for internal source code control and defect tracking.
- Developed an Asynchronous Messaging over SCSI protocol to facilitate peer-to-peer storage mirroring.

## Junior Software Engineer, IBM

Tucson, AZ - 2001 - 2002

Developed device drivers for IBM tape backup products on Solaris and Linux platforms.

## Distance Education Technician

South Dakota School of Mines and Technology Rapid City, SD — 1998 - 2000

- · Developed leading edge Internet based distance courses.
- Installed and maintained audio / video networks related to the encoding and distribution of college courses.

## Research Assistant – Atmospheric Science Department

South Dakota School of Mines and Technology Rapid City, SD — 1996 - 1998

- Programmed image processing software using C++ and IDL.
- · Gained proficiency on Silicon Graphics (SGI) and SUN workstations.

## **Education**

## Walden University

Master of Science (MS), Computer Engineering — 2004 - 2007

Specialization in Computer Architecture. In depth study of CPU design, Networks, Parallel Computing, Programming Language Design, and Embedded systems.

## South Dakota School of Mines and Technology

Bachelor of Science (BS), Computer Engineering - 1996 - 2001

#### **Patents**

## Priority initialization system

United States 7,383,404 — Issued June 3, 2008 Barnes et al.

## Method, system, and program for throttling data transfer

United States 7,194,562 — Issued March 20, 2007

Barnes et al.

# **Recent Open Source Projects**

# github.com/jefbarn/pgx\_json\_schema

A JSON Schema validator for Postgres implemented in Rust

# github.com/jefbarn/moment-recur-ts

Date recurrence library written in Typescript.

# github.com/jefbarn/Sonarr-Menu

Mac status bar utility written in Swift.

## **Personal**

## Career Break

Anchorage, AK — 2012 - 2015

Enjoyed a midlife retirement to pursue adventure sports and world travel.